<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<page title="Who We Are">
  <headsection>
    <p>
      FreeMarker 1 (Classic) was originally written by
      <a href="mailto:beroul@users.sourceforge.net">Benjamin Geer</a> and 
      <a href="classic@zzzcomputing.com">Mike Bayer</a>. They defined the basic 
      syntax -- and more importantly, the philosophy -- of the tool that is 
      carried on in FreeMarker 2. Significant contributions to FreeMarker 
      Classic were made by Nicholas Cull, Holger Arendt and others.
    </p>
    <p>
      In early 2002, <a href="mailto:jon@revusky.com">Jonathan Revusky</a> rewrote the core
      (parser/compiler) code using a popular parser generator tool,
      JavaCC. This was really the basis of FreeMarker 2 (Lazarus),
      which, though largely backward compatible with FreeMarker 1 (Classic)
      is virtually a complete rewrite. Jonathan is also the main
      author and maintainer of the <a href="http://niggle.org">Niggle
      Web Application Framework</a>, a web application framework that
      uses FreeMarker as its view component. He is an independent
      software developer and consultant, available in particular for
      work on java and open-source technologies. He can be reached by email via 
      <a href="mailto:jon@revusky.com">jon at revusky.com</a>
    </p>
    <p>
      <a href="http://www.szegedi.org">Attila Szegedi</a> has made
      significant contributions to the Lazarus release. Besides refactoring and
      optimizing some of the core API's for the Lazarus release,
      Attila is the main author of the date/time support, 
      <tt>freemarker.ext.*</tt> packages responsible for JavaBeans, Jython, and 
      XML mappings, as well as for HTTP servlet, JSP and Ant integration.
    </p>
    <p>
      Dániel Dékány is a rather disputatious, horrid, ever-discontent man. Also he is
      seriously senile and absent-minded. But, he has good insights, and sharp
      eyes to spot the mistakes in the work of <em>other</em> people, and also he is
      technically relatively bright. Many features of FreeMarker are basically his idea,
      or at least was substantially improved based on his feedback. And last
      not least, he is the author of the documentation and the Web page (in
      90%). His English is really bad, but nobody wants to undertake
      these tedious tasks, and anyway, he does it conscientiously. Also,
      despite that he is so thorny, he is helpful if users have problems. So
      finally he is an important contributor to FreeMarker.
    </p>
    <p>
      <a href="http://sixlegs.com/">Chris Nokleberg</a> is a FreeMarker
      "power user" who makes life difficult for the other developers by
      requesting new features and using the BeansWrapper in horrifying
      ways. He attempts to redeem himself by occasionally fixing bugs
      and implementing such features himself.
    </p>
    <p>
       <a href="mailto:stephan@chaquotay.net">Stephan Mueller</a> is
       the author of the new FreeMarker plugin for the Eclipse
       IDE. Stephan studies computer science at the University of Technology
       in Aachen, Germany.
    </p>
    <p>
      Many other ideas and feedback 
      were provided by the various participants on the 
      freemarker-devel and freemarker-user mailing lists. People who are interested 
      in influencing (and even participating in) further  FreeMarker development are strongly 
      encouraged to <a href="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=794">subscribe</a>...
    </p>
    <p>
      By community consensus, FreeMarker 2 release is under the more 
      liberal BSD-style license. (FreeMarker Classic was released under the 
      LGPL.) Benjamin Geer, the main author of FreeMarker 1, remained the 
      copyright holder of FreeMarker versions 2.0.x and 2.1.x. It was decided that, 
      since we did not at that point have a juridical entity (such as the Apache Foundation) 
      to play this role, that Benjamin Geer would continue to be the sole copyright 
      holder. Though various people have contributed to FreeMarker development, to have one 
      individual be copyright holder would make future license changes or 
      clarifications simpler.
    </p>
    <p>
      As of FreeMarker 2.2, the copyright holder of the FreeMarker codebase
      is the <a href="http://www.visigoths.org">Visigoth Software Society</a>, 
      a non-profit association based in Spain, and co-founded by Jonathan Revusky 
      in December of 2002. Benjamin Geer graciously agreed to cede the copyright
      to VSS on the understanding that it would remain available under a liberal
      open-source license. The terms of the license remain the same.
    </p>
  </headsection>
</page>
